Guide to the Frank Tannenbaum Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Frank Tannenbaum Papers,
1915-1969
Tannenbaum, Frank, 1893-1969.
ca. 28,000 items (61 boxes, 33 boxes of note card files)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079387
Biographical Note
Director of University Seminars, professor of Latin American history at Columbia University.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, and subject files of Tannenbaum, including typewritten lists of property records in the various states of Mexico, ca. 1926; and clippings relating to Mexico. Some of these materials were used in the preparation of his book The Mexican Agrarian Revolution. Also, personal letters and files relating to the Farm Security Program, and specifically the Bankhead Bill and the Farm Tenant Bill, 1937, 1934-1937.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 8 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Uncataloged Correspondence
Series III: Seminars
Series IV: Subject Files
Series V: Folders in the Subject Files
Series VI: Manuscripts
Series VII: Card Files
Series VIII: Scrapbooks/Photograph Albums
Subjects
Columbia University--Faculty.; Mexico--Economic conditions.; Mexico--Social conditions.; Real property--Mexico.; Farm tenancy--United States.; Agriculture--United States.; Agricultural laws and legislation--United States.; College teachers.; Historians.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-95. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1969 M-69 Tannenbaum, Frank Bequest
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Armstrong, Hamilton Fish To Frank Tannenbaum, New York, 1944-1963, (8 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Beard, Charles Austin To Frank Tannenbaum, New Milford & New York, 8 June [n.y.] & 14 April 1918, (1 a.l.s., 1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Bowles, Chester To Frank Tannenbaum, Essex, CT, 5 May 1955, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Bowles, Chester To Frank Tannenbaum, Essex, CT, 2 June 1955, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Brandeis, Alice Goldmark To Frank Tannenbaum, Chatham, MA, 26 June [n.y.] & 6 Aug. 1932, (1 p.c.s., 1 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Brandeis, Louis Dembitz To Frank Tannenbaum, Chatham, MA & Washington, DC, 19 May 1929 - 4 Sept. 1931, (4 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Busch, German To Frank Tannenbaum, La Paz, Bolivia, 15 August 1939, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Calles, Plutarco Elias To Frank Tannenbaum, Mexico City, 26 July 1928, (1 telegram) (Box 1)
  - Camacho, Manuel Avila To Frank Tannenbaum, Mexico City, 25 January 1943, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Cardenas, Lazaro To Frank Tannenbaum, [v.p.], 1928-1969, (60 letters) (Box 1)
  - Cardenas, Lazaro [Como consecuencia del estudio minuciose que he efectuado a traves del recorrido por Tamaulipas y Nueve Leona], Dr. Arroyo, N. L., Mexico, 16 July 1936, (8 page t.ms. (carbon)) (Box 1)
  - Cardenas, Lazaro [La Revolucion Cubana], Mexico City, 28 April 1961, (4 page t.ms. (thermofax copy)) (Box 1)
  - Daniels, Josephus To Frank Tannenbaum, [v.p.], 1933-1942, (8 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Debbs, Theodore To Frank Tannenbaum, Terre Haute, Indiana, 1921 & 1922, (4 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Dewey, John To Frank Tannenbaum, New York & Key West, [n.y.]; 1917-1938, (4 a.l.s., 6 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Dos Passos, John To Frank Tannenbaum, Westmoreland, VA, 30 Oct. 1956, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Eastman, Max To Frank Tannenbaum, New York & Croton, NY, [n.d.] & 1915-1932, (2 a.l.s., 2 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Feis, Herbert To Frank Tannenbaum, [v.p.], 1933-1957, (1 a.l.s., 2 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Figueres, Jose To Frank Tannenbaum, [Costa Rica], 12 July 1956, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Frankfurter, Felix To Frank Tannenbaum, Cambridge, MA & Washington, DC, 1929-1950, (3 a.l.s., 3 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Gardner, John W To Frank Tannenbaum, New York, 28 Feb. 1950, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Goldberg, Arthur To Frank Tannenbaum, Washington, DC, 12 July 1962, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Greene, Graham C. To Frank Tannenbaum, London, 22 April 1964, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Gruening, Ernest To Frank Tannenbaum, New York & Portland, Maine, 1925-1928, (3 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Hughes, Charles Evans To Frank Tannenbaum, Washington, DC, 20 October 1923, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Lewis, John Llewellyn To Frank Tannenbaum, Indianapolis, IN, 21 Feb. 1925, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Lippman, Walter To Frank Tannenbaum, New York, 1917-1929, (3 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Meade, Margaret To Frank Tannenbaum, New York, 22 Feb. 1968, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Meany, George To Frank Tannenbaum, Washington, DC, 10 March & 22 April 1960, (1 t.l.s., 1 telegram) (Box 1)
  - Nevins, Allan To Frank Tannenbaum, San Marino, CA, 7 Feb. 1957, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Rivera, Diego To Frank Tannenbaum, [n.p.], 31 Aug. 1931, (1 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson Aldrich To Frank Tannenbaum, New York, 1948 & 1949, (4 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano To Frank Tannenbaum, [v.p.], 1929 & 1930, (4 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, Jr. To Frank Tannenbaum, San Juan, PR, 1 Sept. 1931, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Rusk, Dean To Frank Tannenbaum, New York, 31 July 1952, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Shotwell, James T. To Frank Tannenbaum, New York & Mexico, 1932-1950, (16 t.l.s., 1 t.l. (carbon)) (Box 1)
  - Tannenbaum, Frank To Josephus Daniels, [n.p.] & Mexico City, 1936-1941, (4 t.l.) (Box 1)
  - Tawney, Richard Henry To Frank Tannenbaum, Oxford, England, 27 Sept. 1921, (1 a.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Thomas, Norman To Frank Tannenbaum, New York, 22 Oct. 1963, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Untermeyer, Louis To Frank Tannenbaum, New York, 20 Aug. 1916, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Vasconcelos, Jose To Frank Tannenbaum, Mexico City, 7 Nov. 1924, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Wald, Lillian D. To Frank Tannenbaum, New York, 5 March & 16 April 1925, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Wallace, Henry Agard To Frank Tannenbaum, Washington, DC, [n.d.] & 26 March 1942, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
  - Wells, Sumner To Frank Tannenbaum, [v.p.], 1938-1950, (14 t.l.s., 1 t.l. (incomplete)) (Box 1)
  - Wirtz, William Willard To Frank Tannenbaum, Washington, DC, 24 Oct. 1963, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 1)
- Series II: Uncataloged Correspondence
  - Adler, Felix -- Barnes, Harry Elmer -- Beales, Carlton -- Hayes, Carlton Joseph Huntley -- Herring, Herbert Clinton -- Keppel, Frederick Paul -- Knopf, Alfred A. -- Osborne, Thomas Mott -- Peabody, George Foster -- Putnam, George Palmner
  - Beckworth, A.R. -- Brookings Institute -- Canaday, Frank & Ward -- Center of Latin American Economic & Historical Studies -- Chandler, Alfred D. -- Congratulatory Letters on Publications (Misc.) -- Doherty, Mary L. -- Fernandez, Hugo -- Foreign Relations Committee (U. S. Senate) -- Freedgood, Seymour -- Freyre, Gilberto -- de Galindez, Jesus -- Institute of Pan-American History & Geography -- Jobs -- Knopf, Alfred A. -- Mexico, Misc. Correspondence -- Misadventure--27 June 1966 -- New School -- North Carolina, Univ. of -- Office of Inter-American Affairs -- O'Gorman, Juan -- Olinger, Chauncy -- Pellecer, Carlos Manuel -- People to People Program -- Pietri, A.U. -- Praeger Publications -- Response to PSQ Article -- Rickey, Branch--The Jackie Robinson Story -- Rockefeller Foundation -- Rockefeller Foundation--Stacy May -- Rutgers University -- Schlesinger, Arthur M., Jr. -- School of International Affairs -- Siempre -- Spanish Institute and Pavilion -- State Dept. -- Stulman, Julius -- Tannenbaum, Frank-- Letters of Recommendation -- Theobald, Robert -- Toledano, Lanpardo -- Townsend, W. Cameron -- War Dept. -- Watson, Goodwin -- World War II (letters by F.T.)
  - A - F, 1914-1933 (Box 2)
  - G - M, 1914-1933 (Box 3)
  - N - S, 1914-1933 (Box 4)
  - T - Z, 1914-1933 (Box 5)
  - A & B, 1934-1969 (Box 6)
  - C & D, 1934-1969 (Box 7)
  - E - G, 1934-1969 (Box 8)
  - de Galindez - H, 1934-1969 (Box 9)
  - I - Knopf (1), 1934-1969 (Box 10)
  - Knopf (2) - M (1), 1934-1969 (Box 11)
  - M (2) & N, 1934-1969 (Box 12)
  - O - Q, 1934-1969 (Box 13)
  - R - S (1), 1934-1969 (Box 14)
  - S (2) - Sz, 1934-1969 (Box 15)
  - T & U, 1934-1969 (Box 16)
  - V - Z, 1934-1969 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence and Reviews Pertaining to the Published Works of Frank Tannenbaum (Box 18)
- Series III: Seminars
  - University Seminars (Box 19)
  - Latin American Seminars (1) (Box 20)
  - Latin American Seminars (2) (Box 21)
- Series IV: Subject Files
  - A - American P (Box 22)
  - American S Arg (Box 23)
  - Arg - Balance of Power (Box 24)
  - Balance of Power - Bolivia (Box 25)
  - Bolivia - Brazil (Box 26)
  - Bri - Clippings (Box 27)
  - Columbia - Com (Box 28)
  - Con - Council on Foreign Relations (Box 29)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Council on World Tensions (Box 30)
  - Cour - Cuba (Box 31)
  - De - Ferment (Box 32)
  - Fi - Fo (Box 33)
  - Fr - Hac (Box 34)
  - Haiti - Institutions (Box 35)
  - mt - J (Box 36)
  - Labor (Box 37)
  - Latin America (Box 38)
  - Latin American, A - Z (Box 39)
  - Li - Mexico (Box 40)
  - Mexico (Box 41)
  - Mi - Ne (Box 42)
  - 0 - Peru (Box 43)
  - Peru (Box 44)
  - Peru - Pl (Box 45)
  - Pol - Race (Box 46)
  - Re Sc (Box 47)
  - Se - So (Box 48)
  - Speaking mangagement (Box 49)
  - Ten - Uruguay (Box 50)
  - Us - Z (Box 51)
- Series V: Folders in the Subject Files
  - Academia Nacional de Historia (Venezuela) -- Accion International -- Ad Hoc Committee -- Natl. Academy of Sciences -- Advertising Council -- Agrarismo, Indiaismo y Nacionalismo -- Agriculture -- Amazon -- American Assembly -- American Council for Emigres in Professions, Inc. -- American Metal Co. -- American Press Institute -- American Society of Criminology -- American Traditions in Foreign Policy -- American University -- Anaconda Co. -- Argentina -- Art -- Balance of Power -- Balance of Power - Caste in India -- Balance of rower - Church -- Balance of Power - Conclusion -- Balance of Power - Family -- Balance of Power - Liberty -- Balance of Power - Seminar, l945-1946 -- Balance of tower - Seminar, 1950 -- Balance of Power-- Seminar 1954 -- Balance of Power - Social Change -- Balance of Power - State -- Balance of Power - War -- Balance of Power - Bibliography -- Balance of Power in Society -- Bankhead Bill -- Bibliography - Latin America -- Biographical Data -- Bolivia -- Bolivia - Jesuit Missions -- Book Projects -- Brazil -- British West Indies -- Cabot Awards -- Canadian Institute of Public Affairs -- Candillo, the -- Carribean Hurricane Project -- Cartoons -- Center for Inter-American Relations -- Center Letter -- Center of Latin American Economic and Historical Studies - Articles -- Center of Latin American Economic and Historical Studies - Gifts -- Center of Latin American Economic and Historical. Studies - Project -- Central America, International Relations -- Chile -- Clippings, Misc. -- Colombia -- Columbia Univ. - Official -- Columbia Univ. - Journalism world -- Columbia Univ. Press -- Committees, Memberships -- Common Experience in the western Hemisphere -- Conference Board, the -- Conference on Latin American History -- Costa Rica -- Council for the Study of Mankind -- Council on Foreign Relations -- Council on Foreign Relations - Colonies -- Council on Foreign Relations - Latin America -- Council on World Tensions -- Course Announcements -- Crime and the Community -- Criminology -- Cuba -- Decline of Spanish Power -- Department of History -- Dominican Republic -- Dominican Republic - American Investments -- Ecuador -- Economy -- Economic Development -- Economics -- Education -- Education in Latin America -- European Social Politics -- Examinations, H196 -- Ferment in Latin America -- Finance -- Foreign Affairs -- Foreign Affairs Quarterly -- Foreign Investments - Latin America -- Ford Foundation -- Foundation for Human Resources Development, Inc. -- Foundation for Study of Human Organization, Inc. -- France -- Freedom House -- Fundacion Creole -- Government -- Guatamala -- Guatamala - Seminario de Integracion Social -- Guggenheim Foundation -- Hacienda, the -- Haiti -- Hammarskold Forum -- Historical problems in Latin America -- Honduras -- Hopper, the -- Human Nature -- Ideologists -- Indian, Origin of the Amazon -- Industrialism -- Institutions -- Inter-American Association for Democracy and Freedom -- Inter-American Intellectual Cooperation -- International Business Machines -- International Congress of the Americanistas -- International Corporation, the -- International Corporate Body, the -- International Rescue Committee -- Jews in Latin America -- Labor -- Labor - Clippings -- Labor in Latin America -- Latin America -- Latin America Across the Centuries -- Lating America - American Companies -- Latin America - Democracies -- Lating America - Institutions -- Latin America - Policy Proposals -- Latin American Calendar -- Latin American Institute -- Latin American Institutions -- Latin American Institutions, the Developement of -- Latin American Investiments -- Latin American Literature -- Latin American Law -- Latin American Seminar -- Library -- Literature -- Loans -- Louisiana -- Marx, Lenin and Hitler -- Mexican Revolution -- Mexico -- Mexico - Army -- Mexico Book -- Mexico City Confrenece, 1945 -- Mexico City Conference, 1956 & 1957 -- Mexico History -- Mexico, Manuscript Notes -- Minorities -- Miscellaneous clippings -- Miscellaneous notes of F.T. -- Miscellaneous - Not Latin America -- N.B.C. -- N.R.A. Prison Industries Committee -- Negroes in Lating America -- Newsletter, C.U. -- Operation Amigo -- Panama -- Pan American Movement -- Pan America - Clippings -- Parochialism -- Paraguay -- Peru -- Peru D21 -- Peru - Church -- Peru - Civil War -- Peru - Discovery & Conquest -- Peru - Economy -- Peru - Government -- Peru - Geography -- Peru - Inca -- Peru - Independence -- Peru - Modern Economy -- Peru - Outline -- Peru - Parochialism -- Peru - Republic -- Piracy -- Planning -- Political Administration -- Politica1 Stability -- Political Theory -- Political, re: Police -- Politics, Latin America -- Politics and Revolution in Latin America -- Population Policy -- Progress -- Project of the Americas -- Property -- Puerto Rico -- Race -- Race and Population -- Race Problems in Latin America -- Refugees -- Religion -- Research -- Revolution -- Russian Material -- Salvador -- Second World War and Latin America -- Slavery -- Slavery Seminar -- Social Stability -- Society -- Stability, Bibliography -- Spanish Empire -- Spanish Influence, Record of -- Speaking Engagements - 1961 & 1962 -- Speaking Engagements - 1963 -- Speaking Engagements - l964 -- Speaking Engagements - 1965 -- Speaking Engagments - 1966 -- Speaking Engagements - 1968 -- Ten Keys to Latin America -- Ten Keys to Latin America - Enlarged Edition Materials -- Text Book Material on Latin America -- Trade -- Transportations -- Travel -- Trip to Latin America, 1961/62 -- Tropics -- Uruguay -- United States, the Case of -- Venezuela -- Weatherlands Lectures -- Westinghouse Broadcasting Company -- West Point -- West Point Class -- West Point Students -- Wither Latin America
- Series VI: Manuscripts
  - Manuscripts: Political Stability (Box 51A & 51B)
  - Manuscripts (Box 52)
  - Manuscripts (Box 53)
  - Manuscripts (Box 54)
  - Printed Materials (Box 54)
  - Printed Materials (Box 55)
  - Printed Materials (Box 56)
  - Diaries (Box 57)
  - Appointment Books (Box 57)
  - Photographs (Box 57)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 57)
  - Meeting In Memoriam of Professor Frank Tannenbauin, 1970 (Box 57)
  - Mexican Property Records, States, A - Q (Box 1) (Box 58)
  - Mexican Property Records, States, R - Z (Box 2) (Box 59)
  - Clippings Relating to Mexico (1) (Box 60)
  - Clippings Relating to Mexico (2) (Box 61)
  - Farm Security Program (Box 61)
- Series VII: Card Files
  - Countries: A - C; E - S (Box 62)
  - Countries: Brazil - Mexico (Box 63)
  - Countries: Peru - Topical (Box 64)
  - Slavery, England (Box 65)
  - Latin American Institutions (Box 66)
  - Latin America, General Topics (Box 67)
  - Peru (Box 68)
  - Inter-American Affairs (Box 69)
  - Unclassified (Box 70)
  - Peru (Box 71)
  - West Indies (Box 72)
  - Political Stability (Box 73)
  - Central America; Chile; Bolivia; Paraguay (Box 74)
  - Peru (Box 75)
  - Latin American Countries (Box 76)
  - Mexico (Box 77)
  - Mexico (Box 78)
  - Foreign Affairs (Box 79)
  - Peru (Box 80)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 81)
  - Agricultural Labor Before Revolutions (Box 82)
  - Agricultural Legislation (Box 83)
  - Agriculture (Box 84)
  - Church; Miscellaneous (Box 85)
  - Argentina (Box 86)
  - Slavery (Box 87)
  - Colombia (Box 88)
  - Ecuador; Venezuela (Box 89)
  - Labor (Box 90)
  - Crime (Box 91)
  - Industrialization (Box 92)
  - Brazil (Box 93)
  - Mexico (Box 94)
- Series VIII: Scrapbooks/Photograph Albums
  - Photograph Album of Instituto Central (Box 95)
  - Scrapbook (mostly photographs) (Box 95)
  - Scrapbook: "Album Historico Geografico" Sarah Orestes Rosas (Box 95)